<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mraoaakash.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mraoaakash.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-09-03T12:11:06+00:00</updated><id>https://mraoaakash.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Aakash M. Rao</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Computer Science at Ashoka University</title><link href="https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2023/CS-at-Ashoka/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computer Science at Ashoka University"/><published>2023-08-18T11:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T11:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2023/CS-at-Ashoka</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2023/CS-at-Ashoka/"><![CDATA[<p>Computer Science at Ashoka is one of the few fields that goes under the radar in most situations. The involvement of its students with other departments often leads to it being overshadowed by the existence of that other department. For instance, a large number of students work with the Trivedi School of Biosciences on various computational projects. But there is virtually no branding of the department present in those spaces.</p> <p>This blog-post is aimed at prospective students, freshmen and maybe even the sophomore students to give them a taste of what it is to get through their time in CS@AU.</p> <h3 id="getting-in">Getting In:</h3> <p>Getting in is not the most difficult thing, as you know it, some of you are already here. Ashoka is one of the few universities in India that has a holistic approach to admission. Believe me, if not for this process, and if it followed the conventional academics-first process, I would have never gotten in. I am not going to spend too much time on this because this part has been covered extensively by many other people.</p> <h3 id="your-first-year">Your first year:</h3> <p>Ashoka mandates that you do a series of foundational courses to gain knowledge of different disciplines. If you are here for that, and are not sure what you want to do with your time at Ashoka, then these courses are the best thing for you. However, if you are someone like me and are sure that you want to get on with CS, you will be in for a surprise. The Foundational Courses (or FCs as they call it) are really good, they are absolutely brilliant courses exposing you to some of the most amazing work. However, they are daunting and can be a real burden if you find them uninteresting or a burden.</p> <p>I faced major challenges because of this because I never enjoyed qualitative FCs, I preferred the FCs dealing with the sciences and math. I highly recommend you chose the courses more in line with your interest from among the ones offered. Each FC has 4 or 5 professors offering them with different approaches. Take the one which most suits your interests.</p> <p>In your first semester, the Monsoon, you will be required to only take FC. However, in your second semester you can take your first set of introductory courses in CS. The first two courses you will be exposed to are Introduction to Computer Programming and Discrete Mathematics. These two courses are the foundational courses of your time at AU. You must do this to your best and fullest extent as they lay the foundation for the rest of your knowledge.</p> <h3 id="your-next-three-years">Your next three years:</h3> <p>Over your next three years, you will spend taking a wide variety of courses from various sub-areas of computer science as well as some interdisciplinary fields. All these courses are usually well thought out and well structured, with the rare exception.</p> <p>The professors teaching at Ashoka are brilliant minds and researchers in their fields, however this does not always translate to their teaching abilities. Some of the best researchers at Ashoka are not the best teachers. You have a set of core courses that you must accomplish and a set of electives that you may take. The composition of the required courses changes periodically, especially with the implementation of the NEP and now a 4 year degree, hence, I will refrain from commenting on structure.</p> <p>The core courses of CS cover most broad areas that CS has to offer and can be called equivalent in subject matter to that of any other university in the world. However, I find the degree of rigour varies widely by course as well as the professor offering the course. The same course offered in two semesters may or may not be the same, in terms of rigor or material. The department is working to standardize a working template for the core courses to ensure that this variability is removed.</p> <p>The same applies to the electives, however, a constant issue over the years has been a severe lack of specialized electives being offered. This has been slowly changing and will hopefully get better as time progresses.</p> <h3 id="issues-with-the-department">Issues with the department:</h3> <p>CS@AU is regarded heavily as a space for research with most people stepping into research in their junior and senior years. If you are here expecting the same job prospects as someone doing a BTech, please change your thought process. The intertwining of industry and Ashoka does exists to some degree, however, it exists in the context of research. This makes it difficult for people getting out of the university to find relevant roles.</p> <p>While research is heavily in the scope of the department, it is very difficult for undergraduate students to find any form of funding to support their research interests, if they do not overlap with that of a professor. This is not an issue with Ashoka, but more of an issue with the education system in India.</p> <p>The department does support undergraduate research independently but fails to support any external achievements such as conferences, publications, and other minor grants. I have personally been unable to go to present my work at a conference due to funding and grant issues.</p> <h3 id="issues-with-the-culture">Issues with the culture:</h3> <p>The culture of Computer Science at Ashoka is very weird. It is not welcoming, it is cutthroat, and no one will support you through your journey. It is very real world like, which arguably has its benefits. You are given complete autonomy over every decision you make, right from courses you take (after your first semester), to the research you participate in, to your friend circle. So please make the right choices. This autonomy given to students does have it’s perks, but also numerous issues. Figuring that out is a learning experience and I would not want to take it away from you.</p> <p>Just know that the change in scenery has two outcomes: You have kids who already had high degrees of freedom at their home, and continue to have that here. They do great and are great people in most cases. There are obviously some exceptions. You have kids who have experienced parental control and restricted freedom, who now have been given complete freedom. They are people you need to be weary of, obviously there are exceptions here as well. Not everyone runs around like headless chickens.</p> <h3 id="to-conclude">To conclude:</h3> <p>CS@AU is great, the complaints I have about it aren’t life altering but just inconveniences that won’t matter a few years down the road. If you’re here it’s great. Make the most of it</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="information"/><category term="information"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How your time with CS@Ashoka will look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mraoaakash.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>